Rudolph Troike Bilingual Education Collection 1953-1988 (bulk 1974-1988)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Rudolph Troike Bilingual Education Collection 1953-1988, (bulk 1974-1988)
MS 473
Troike, Rudolph C.
Rudolph C. Troike, a linguistics specialist, accumulated many materials throughout his professional career that pertains to bilingual education and bilingualism in the twentieth century. This collection contains materials that follow the evolution of bilingual education in the United States and around the world. Correspondence, research files, periodicals, reports, and manuals are some of the types of materials found within the collection. The collection focuses on the planning, evaluation, policy making, and program development of bilingual education.
16 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
Rudolph C. Troike, a linguistics specialist, was born in 1933 in Brownsville, Texas. He attended the University of Texas, Austin where he received his B.A. and M.A. degrees in Anthropology and Ph.Ds in German Linguistics and Anthropology. For his graduate studies, he participated in a two year anthropological study and aided in archeological excavations through the Escuela Nacional de Antropología e Historia, Mexico. Afterwards, he worked with the Georgetown University English Language Program in Turkey for three years. Troike then returned to the University of Texas, where he became a full professor in 1971 in English and Linguistics, an appointment he held for ten years after. He was appointed as the director of the Center for Applied Linguistics in Washington, D.C. from 1972-1977. During this time he hosted the first visit by linguists and language teachers from China, and was U.S. delegate to two UNESCO conferences. In 1980 he moved to the University of Illinois, where he was director of the graduate program in bilingual education. In 1989 he relocated to the University of Arizona where he served as Head of the Department of English from 1990 to 1995. Currently he is the director of the English Language/Linguistics Program at the University of Arizona. His principal research interests are in American Indian languages and the ethnohistory of south Texas and northeastern Mexico, and in universals in syntax.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 3 series.
Series I: Personal 1969-1988, undated
Series II: Publications 1957-1988, undated
Subseries 1: Dissertations and Theses
Subseries 2: Instructional Materials
Subseries 3: Periodicals, Newsletters, and Bulletins
Subseries 4: Reports and Evaluations
Series III: Research Files 1953-1988, undated
Subseries 1: Conference Materials
Subseries 2: Ethnic Groups
Subseries 3: Federal and State Legislations and Regulations
Subseries 4: General Bilingual Education Materials
Subseries 5: International
Subseries 6: Proposals
Subseries 7: United States
Scope and Content Note
The inclusive dates for this collection are 1953-1988, with the bulk of the material dating from 1974-1988. The materials in the collection were collected by Rudolph C. Troike and represent the evolution and history of bilingual education in the twentieth century. This collection contains materials that pertain to the United States and other countries concerning bilingual education and bilingualism. Professional papers and journal articles, reports, case studies, newspaper clippings, periodicals, and other print materials contained in the collection reflect the political and social changes taking place in the twentieth century. These materials were used as research files and resources for Troike and other researchers, teachers, and decision makers involved in bilingual education. The collection focuses on the planning, evaluation, policy making, and program development of bilingual education. Some of the materials in the collection are in other languages such as Spanish, French, and various indigenous languages and are scattered throughout the collection, but are mostly found in series three. Materials in other languages include newspaper and journal articles and school workbooks that were meant to be used in the classroom.
Access Terms
Troike, Rudolph C.
Bilingual education and bilingualism
Bilingual education--United States
Bilingual education--United States--Handbooks, manuals, etc.
Bilingualism--Case studies
Bilingualism--Political aspects
Bilingualism--Social aspects
Bilingualism--Research--Methodology
Bilingualism--United States
Bilingualism--Latin America—History
Education, Bilingual
Language and languages--Study and teaching--Bilingual method
Container List
- Series I: Personal, 1969-1988; undated
  This series is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. It contains Rudolph Troike’s personal correspondence and materials concerning his professional achievements.
  - Certificate for Participation, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1988; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Who’s Who in Bilingual Education, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Publications, 1957-1988; undated
  This series is arranged topically and alphabetically. It contains dissertations, theses, reports, and evaluations written by various authors and organizations on the subject of bilingual education and bilingualism. Periodicals, newsletters, and bulletins collected and subscribed to by Troike are represented in the collection. Also present are instructional and informational materials for teachers concerning bilingual education and implementation.
  - Subseries 1: Dissertations and Theses
    - Bibliographies and Guidelines, 1981; undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bilingual Education in Palmetto City: A Case Study by Jesse J. Hargrove, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dissertation on 1978 Bilingual Education Act by Iris Berke-Part I, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dissertation on 1978 Bilingual Education Act by Iris Berke-Part II, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - English Reading Achievement in a Bilingual School by Jane H. Canseco, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - An Effectiveness Study of English as a Second Language (ESL) and Chinese Bilingual Methods by John B. Lum, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Evaluation into Policy: Bilingual Education 1978 by Iris Berke, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Legislation and the Language of Instruction in Texas Schools by Marilyn Ann McGivney, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Outstanding Dissertations in Bilingual Education, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Outstanding Dissertations in Bilingual Education, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Outstanding Dissertations in Bilingual Education, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Parent and Family Influences on Academic Achievement Among Mexican American Students by William Lloyd Kimball, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - A Policy Study of Bilingual Education: 1953-1983 by Colman Brez Stein Jr. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 2: Instructional Materials
    - Catalogs for Bilingual Classroom Materials, 1976; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Center for Law and Education-Bilingual Bicultural Education: A Handbook for Attorneys and Community Workers, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Curriculum Building Materials, 1975-1978; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Education Service Center Language Development Institute- Accutrak Texas Criterion Reference System for Oral Language-Manual for Administering the Tests, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Teacher Guidelines for Bilingual Programs, 1970; 1977-1978,; undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - EPIE Institute-Selector’s Guide for Bilingual Education Materials Volume I Spanish Language Arts, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - EPIE Institute-Selector’s Guide for Bilingual Education Materials Volume II Spanish Branch Programs, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - EPIE Institute-Selector’s Guide for Bilingual Education Materials Volume III The Status of Programs in Chinese, Japanese, Korean, and Vietnamese, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Office of the Superintendent of Public Instruction-Teaching Cultural Concepts in Spanish Class, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Student Assessment Materials, 1978-1980; undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Teacher Competencies and Training Materials, 1966; 1974-1979,; 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Tucson Unified School District-Bilingual Instruction and Special English Training, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - U.S Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-Practical Guide to Measuring Project Impact on Student Achievement, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 3: Periodicals, Newsletters, and Bulletins
    - Agenda: A Journal of Hispanic Issues, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - American Indian Bilingual Education Center Newsletter, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Anishinaabe Giigidowin Newsletter, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Arizona State University-Center for Indian Education Newsletter, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - The Atlantic, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - BIA Education Research Bulletins, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Bilingual/English as a Second Language Reporter, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Bilingual Journal, 1977-1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Bureau of Bilingual Education-Multilingual Multicultural, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Cartel: Annotated Bibliography of Bilingual Bicultural Materials, 1974-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Center for Applied Linguistics-The Linguistic Reporter, 1975-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Center for Law and Education Inc. Newsletter, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Chess and Associates Inc.-Chess Moves, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - The Chicano Education Project-Un Nuevo Día, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - The Civil Rights Quarterly-Perspectives, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Council of Communication Societies-Communication Notes, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Defensa- Bulletin of the National League Defenders of the Spanish Language, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Delta Kappa Gamma Bulletin, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Early Childhood Bilingual Education Project Office-Doble, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - East-West Culture Institute-Culture and Language Learning Newsletter, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - East-West Culture Institute-Language Planning Newsletter, 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Education Commission of the States- Legislative Review, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Education Libraries, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Educational Researcher, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - English as a Second Language/Native Language Arts/Music Language Arts Newsletter, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - ERIC/CLL News Bulletin, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - European Community Action Programme Newsletter, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Federal Register, 1976-1988 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Foreign Language Annuals, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Harvard University-Inequality in Education, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Illinois Resource Center for Teachers of Language Minority Students-Linguathon, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Indian Education Resources Center Bulletin, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Institute for Research on Educational Finance and Governance Newsletter, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Intercultural Development Research Association Newsletter, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - International Bureau of Education-Educational Documentation and Information Bulletin, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - National Advisory Council on Indian Education Newsletter, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - National Association for Bilingual Education-Nabe News, 1978-1987 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - National Center for Education Statistics Bulletin, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Focus, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Forum, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Forum, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Forum, 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Forum, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Memo, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - National Dissemination and Assessment Center Department of Health Education Welfare-Bilingual Resources, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - National Institute for Multicultural Education Newsletter, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - National Puerto Rican Coalition Newsletter, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Prep Bilingual Education, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Society for Research in Child Development-Washington Report, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Teachers of English to Speakers of Other Languages (TESOL) Newsletter, 1970-1976 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The University of San Francisco School of Education-The Multicultural Program, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - The University of Texas-Bilingual Special Education Newsletter, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - U.S Department of Commerce-Nosotros…We…, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Washington Social Legislation Bulletin, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 4: Reports and Evaluations
    - American Institutes for Research-Evaluation of Bilingual Education Programs the Impact Study, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - American Institutes for Research-Evaluation of Bilingual Education Programs the Exemplary Study, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Association for School, College, and University Staffing-Teacher Supply and Demand a Report Based Upon an Opinion Survey of Teacher Placement Officers, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - The Bilingual Cross Cultural Education Committee-Commission for Teacher Preparation and Licensing: A Report of Bilingual Cross Cultural Educational Credentialing Requirements, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Bilingual Education Service Center-DSA VI a Profile of Bilingual Education in the Midwest, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Center for Applied Linguistics-Educational Policy and Political Acceptance: The Imposition of English as the Language of Instruction in American Schools by Arnold Leibowitz, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Child Development Associate Consortium-The Identification of Competencies for Child Development Associates Working with Chicano Children Final Report, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Congressional Research Service-Overview of Federal Bilingual Education Programs and Participants, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - The Dissemination and Assessment Center for Bilingual Education-Summary Report on the National Assessment Survey of Title VII ESEA, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Education Study Center-Development of Bilingual Bicultural Education Models Final Report, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Educational Policy Development Center-The Availability of Bilingual Education Teachers: Implications for Title VI Enforcement and Good Educational Practice Final Report, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Educational Policy Research Center-State Compensatory Education and Bilingual Programs, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - GAO-Briefing Report of Bilingual Education a New Look at the Research Evidence, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - InterAmerica-Research Associates-Assessing Successful Strategies in Bilingual Vocational Training Programs Final Report, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - InterAmerica-Projections of Number of Limited English Proficient Persons to the Year 2000 Report and Methodology, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - InterAmerica-Projections of Number of Limited English Proficient Persons to the Year 2000 Report Appendices, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Intercultural Development Research Association-Bilingual Education Cost and Analysis Report for the Office of Bilingual Education, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - International Association of Applied Linguistics-Psycholinguistics Review Volume Three, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Issues of Language Assessment: Foundations and Research-Proceedings of the First Annual Language Assessment Institute, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - National Advisory and Coordinating Council on Bilingual Education-Ninth Annual Report, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - National Advisory Committee on the Education of Bilingual Education-Second Annual Report, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - National Advisory Council on Bilingual Education-Second Annual Report, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - National Advisory Council on Bilingual Education-Third Annual Report, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - National Advisory Council on Bilingual Education- Fourth Annual Report, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - National Advisory Council on Bilingual Education-The Prospects for Bilingual Education in the Nation Fifth Annual Report, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - National Association of Bilingual Education-Report on Bilingual Education Issues for Administrators: A Media Review, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Analysis of National Data Sets Progress Report Volume II, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Bilingual Education Studies Progress Report Volume III, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Communication/Dissemination Progress Report Volume IV, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Fourth Quarterly Progress Report Volume I, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-National Center for Bilingual Research Annual Report Volume I, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-National Center for Bilingual Research Annual Report Volume II, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-National Center for Bilingual Research Annual Report Volume III, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-National Center for Bilingual Research Annual Report Volume IV, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Report of the Research Planning Workshop, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Report on the Study of Limited Language Proficiency, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Semiannual Progress Report for the Period May 15 to November 15, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Success in Bilingual Education Programs NCBR/CONAC, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Synthesis of Reported Evaluation and Research Evidence of the Effectiveness of Bilingual Education Basic Projects Volume I, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Synthesis of Reported Evaluation and Research Evidence of the Effectiveness of Bilingual Education Basic Projects Volume II, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - National Center for Bilingual Research-Third Quarterly Performance Report Volume III, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - National Center for Education Statistics-The Bilingual Education Program Information Report, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - National Center for Education Statistics-Contractor Report: Projections of Non English Language Background Persons in the U.S to the Year 2000, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - National Center for Education Statistics-A Project to Develop a Measure of English Language Proficiency Final Report, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - National Center for Education Statistics-State Education Agencies and Language Minority Students, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-First Annual Report, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Quarterly Report, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Quarterly Report, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Strengthening Bilingual Education, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - National Clearinghouse for Bilingual Education-Strengthening Bilingual Education: A Report from the Commissioner of Education to the Congress and the President, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Southwest Council of Foreign Language Teachers-Reports on Social, Psychological, Linguistic, and Pedagogical Barriers, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Southwest Educational Development Laboratory-Lau Task Force Report: Cognitive Style Implications for Educational Research, Treatment of Language Minority Students, Teacher Training, and Policy Recommendations, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Strength through Wisdom: A Report to the President from the President’s Commission on Foreign Language and International Studies, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - SWRL Educational Research and Development-Program Impact Evaluations: An Introduction for Managers of Title VII Projects, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - United States Census Bureau-Supplementary Report for Provisional Estimates of Social, Economic, and Housing Characteristics of States and Selected Standard Metropolitan Statistical Areas, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - U.S Department of Education-The Condition of Bilingual Education in the Nation: A Report from the Secretary of Education to the President and the Congress, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - U.S Department of Education-The Condition of Bilingual Education in the Nation: A Report from the Secretary of Education to the President and the Congress, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - U.S Department of Education-A Study of Teacher Training Programs in Bilingual Education Volume II RMC Report, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - U.S Department of Education-Descriptive Phase Report of the National Longitudinal Evaluation of the Effectiveness of Services for Language Minority Limited English Proficient Students, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - U.S Department of Education Office of Planning, Budget, and Evaluation-Critiques of the Final Draft Report on the Effectiveness of Bilingual Education: A Review of the Literature, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - U.S Department of Education Office of Planning, Budget, and Evaluation-Final Draft Report on the Effectiveness of Bilingual Education: A Review of the Literature, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - U.S Department of Education Office of Planning, Budget, and Evaluation-First Rough Draft of the Report on the Effectiveness of Bilingual Education: A Review of the Literature, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - U.S Department of Education Office of Planning, Budget, and Evaluation-Second Rough Draft of the Report on the Effectiveness of Bilingual Education: A Review of the Literature, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - U.S Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-The Assimilation of American Language Minorities: Structure, Pace, and Extent, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - U.S Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-The Condition of Bilingual Education in the Nation First Report by the U.S Commissioner of Education to the President and the Congress, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - U.S Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-The Condition of Bilingual Education in the Nation Second Annual Report by the U.S Commissioner of Education to the President and the Congress, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - U.S Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-Interim Report a Bilingual Education: A Handbook for Educators, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - U.S Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-A Process Evaluation of the Bilingual Education Program Title VII Elementary and Secondary Education Act Volume I, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - U.S Department of Health, Education, and Welfare-The Status of Bilingual Vocational Training Report of the Commissioner of Education and the Secretary of Labor to the President and to the Congress, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)